A Guide to the Population Council records, Central Files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 1 to Series 4 FA432
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council records, Central Files, Accession 2, RG 2, Series 1 to Series 4
1941, 1957-1983
bulk 1966-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Population Council
FA432
384.69 Cubic Feet
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Population Council document its day-to-day operation as an organization that, among other activities, evaluated and administered grants; sponsored conferences of scholars in the field of population control; and provided advice to individuals, private institutions, and governments concerned with population. There is some material relating to major policy decisions of the Council. There are also letters and reports from scientists involved in medical research and from Council staff members and representatives involved in family planning activities abroad.
The Council records are divided into two accessions. Accession 1, most of which is dated before 1967, consists of material received by the Archive Center in September 1976. Accession 2, most of which is dated after 1966, consists primarily of material received by the Center in April 1977.
The records of Accession 1 and Accession 2 have been kept separate because the Council evidently employed different filing systems in each of the two units and because the existence of the different filing systems sheds light on the manner in which the Council was organized and run. The use of this approach has meant that the files are organized in such a way that material relating to a given topic may appear in several different parts of the collection under either identical names or titles, or under different names or titles. For example, in the case of some institutions whose proper names are in a foreign language, records may have been filed under both the original name and under an English rendering of the name. The files also contain many copies of documents, so that copies of the same item may appear in several places.
To conduct a thorough search for records on a given topic, it is essential to look for material in as many different sections of the collection and under as many different names or titles as possible. For example, material relating to a given organization may be listed under the name of the organization, under the name of important individuals in the organization, or under a title reflecting a study or type of work done by the organization.
Separated Material
Non-textual materials (charts, maps, objects, photographs) have been separated from the paper records. Cross-reference sheets appear among the papers records showing that non-textual items have been removed. Photographs are filed as a separate series.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
If accessing the records of the Population Council, I understand that I am given access to these records on condition that I will not identify by name, either in my research notes or in publication or recording, the names of individuals who received or apparently received medical diagnoses and/or treatments, whose case(s), may be documented or mentioned by personal name in the Population Council records.
Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Accessions include, but are not limited to: 1980:016, 1980:017, 1981:041, 1982:017, 1984:019, 1984:119, 1985:055, 1985:175 and 1987:152.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series:
1. Organization File
2. Foreign Correspondence File
3. Administration File
4. Subject File
Overpopulation; Maternal health services; Economics; Economic development; Federal government -- United States; Family planning; Sociology; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Physiology; Biology -- Research; Fertility; Birth control; Life sciences; Population
- Accession 2, Central Files, 1957-1983; bulk; 2; 286 Cubic Feet
  - Organization File, 1; 17.16 Cubic Feet 39 document boxes.
    Arrangement
    Arranged as received, primarly alphabetical by institutional name.
    Related Materials
    Indexing to the Organization File is provided by FA775 Population Council records, Index, Series 2: Central File Index, 1961-1976.
    - Miscellaneous, 1966-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
    - Agricultural Development Council: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - American Academy of Political and Social Sciences: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - American Eugenics Society: Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - American Friends Service Committee - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - American Friends Service Committee - (Mexican Rector's Visit) Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - American Friends Service Committee - Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - American Institutes for Research: Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - American Medical Association: Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - American Philosophical Society: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - American Public Health Association - Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - American Public Health Association - Commission on Population and Public Health Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - American Universities Field Staff: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Arizona, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Asia Foundation: Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Asia, Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG): Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Asia, Southeast Asia Development Advisory Group (SEADAG): Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Association for Voluntary Sterilization: Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Association of Medical Colleges: Correspondence, 1967-1980 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Baltimore, City of, Health Department: Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Boston University: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Brown University - Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Brown University - Potter, Robert: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Brumbaugh, Graves, Donohue Raymond (Mark Donohue): Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Buffalo, University of: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - California Institute of Technology: Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - California, State Health Department: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - California, University of - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - California, University of - Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - California, University of - Kingsley Davis Correspondence, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - California, University of - Russell Fitzgibbon Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - California, University of - Ronald Freedman Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - California, University of - William Griffiths Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - California, University of - Beryl Roberts Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - California, University of - Helen Wallace Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Carnegie Corporation: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Chicago, University of - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Chicago, University of - Bogue, Donald, Summer Workshops, 1967-1974 (Box 5, Folder 45-48)
    - Chicago, University of - Howser, Phillip: Correspondence, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - China Medical Board: Correspondence, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Church World Service: Correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - City University of New York (CCNY): Correspondence and 2 papers, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 52)
      Scope and Contents
      1 paper on demographic models and policy. 1 paper on forcasting small area population change (computer model) by Professor James Bashers, Sociology at Queens College.
    - Colorado, University of, Institute of Behavioral Science: Correspondence, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Colorado, University of, Medical Center, Cogg, John C.: Correspondence, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Columbia University - Planned Parenthood: Correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Columbia University - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Columbia University - Clifford Nelson: Correspondence, 1967-1969, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Columbia University - Oral History (Bernard Berelson): Correspondence, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Columbia University - Teachers College: Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Commission of Churches on World Affairs: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Commonwealth Fund: Correspondence, 1968-1974 (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Connecticut, University of, Josef Crugler and Donald Wetherall: Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Cornell University: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - Delaware, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Duke University: Correspondence and Reports, 1967-1972 (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - Emory University: Correspondence; Summer 1969 Fellowships, 1967-1973 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Florida State University: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Florida, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Ford Foundation - Correspondence, Grants, 1973-1976 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Ford Foundation - Correspondence, Grants, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Ford Foundation - Correspondence, Grants, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Ford Foundation - Correspondence, Grants, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Ford Foundation - Correspondence, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Ford Foundation - Correspondence, Reports, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Ford Foundation - Oscar Harkavy - Grant Requests, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Ford Foundation - Oscar Harkavy - Reports on visits to: University of Chicago, Cornell University, Georgetown University, Johns Hopkins, University of Michigan, University of North Carolina, University of Pennsylvania, Princeton, Tulane., 1972 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Ford Foundation - Oscar Harkavy - Budget Papers, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Ford Foundation - Oscar Harkavy - Budget Papers, Reports of visits to University of California, University of Chicago, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Ford Foundation - Oscar Harkavy - Correpondence including funding requests, 1968-1970 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Ford Foundation - Leonard Kangas: Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Ford Foundation - News Releases (Grants), 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Ford Foundation - Physiology of Reproduction: Worcester Foundation for Experimental Biology, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Fordham University: Belle Granich, Continuation/Discontinuation of Contraception: Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Gallup Organization: Poll Results; Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - Georgia, University of: Proposal to establish regional population center; proposal for funding "Nonwhite Net Migration Pattern of Counties in the United States, 1950-1960"., 1968-1970 (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - Georgetown, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - George Washington University: Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Gleich Foundation: Correspondence re contributions to Population Council, 1967-1974 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Harvard University: School of Public Health: Correspondence, 1967-1975 (Box 10, Folder 89)
    - Harvard University: Center for Population Studies: Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 10, Folder 90)
    - Harvard University: Medical School, 1966-1968 (Box 10, Folder 91)
    - Hawaii, University of - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 10, Folder 92)
    - Hawaii, University of - East-West Center for Cultural and Technical Interchange: Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 93)
    - Hawaii, University of - East-West Center for Cultural and Technical Interchange: Correspondence, Description of Program, Contract with the USA, 1967-1968 (Box 11, Folder 94)
    - Hawaii, University of - East-West Communication Institute, Population Council Agency Report drafts, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 95)
    - Hawaii, University of - East-West Center Inventory Analysis, 1972-1974 (Box 11, Folder 96)
    - Hawaii, University of - East-West Center for Cultural and Technical Interchange: Correspondence: Conference on Commercial Resources (Hawaii, 1972 December), International Advisory Committee (1972 March), Proposal for Workshop for Training Program (1972 February), 1972-1976 (Box 11, Folder 97)
    - Hawaii, University of - East-West Center, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 98)
    - Illinois, University of - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 12, Folder 99)
    - Illinois, University of - Simon Julian Correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 12, Folder 100)
    - Indiana University: Correspondence, Conference 1967 May, 1967-1972 (Box 12, Folder 101)
    - Institute of International Education: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 102)
    - Institute of Society, Ethics and the Life Sciences: Correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 12, Folder 103)
    - Inter-American Statistical Institute: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 104)
    - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development: Correspondence, University of Chile Demographic Center, 1967-1973 (Box 12, Folder 105)
    - International Committee for Contraception Research: Minutes of Meeting, 1974 October 9-11 (Box 12, Folder 106)
    - International Institute for the Study of Human Reproduction, 1967-1972 (Box 12, Folder 107)
    - International Planned Parenthood Federation, Western Hempisphere: Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 13, Folder 108)
    - International Planned Parenthood Federation, Western Hempisphere: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 13, Folder 109)
    - International Union for the Scientific Study of Population (IUSSP) - Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 13, Folder 110-112)
    - Iowa State University: Correspondence, 1967, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 113)
    - Japan Society, Inc., 1967 (Box 13, Folder 114)
    - Johns Hopkins University: Correspondence, 1972-1975 (Box 14, Folder 115)
    - Johns Hopkins University: Correspondence: Zufir Study, Kanter Study, 1969-1971 (Box 14, Folder 116)
    - Johns Hopkins University: Correspondence 1964, 1967-1968 (Box 14, Folder 117)
    - Johns Hopkins University: Chow, L.P.: Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 14, Folder 118)
    - Johns Hopkins University: Paul Harper: Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 14, Folder 119)
    - Johnson, Larned Foundation Correspondence, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 120)
    - Kansas, University of: Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 14, Folder 120A)
    - Kentucky, University of: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 121)
    - Lalor Foundation: Correspondence, "Uterine Aspiration Procedures", 1967-1971 (Box 14, Folder 122)
    - Louisiana State University: Correspondence, 1970 (Box 14, Folder 123)
    - Macy Foundation: Correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box 15, Folder 124)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT): Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 15, Folder 125)
    - Massachusetts, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 15, Folder 126)
    - Maternity Center Association: Seminar Correspondence, 1968 (Box 15, Folder 127)
    - Miami University: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 15, Folder 128)
    - Michigan State University: Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 15, Folder 129)
    - Michigan, University of - Correspondence: Research Proposals, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 130)
    - Michigan, University of - Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 15, Folder 131)
    - Michigan, University of - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 15, Folder 132)
    - Michigan, University of - Correspondence: Fertility and Family Planning "A World View", 1967 (Box 16, Folder 133)
    - Michigan, University of - Corsa, Dr. Leslie: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 16, Folder 134)
    - Michigan, University of - Freedman, Dr. Ronald: Correspondence, 1966-1972 (Box 16, Folder 135)
    - Michigan, University of - Gillespie, Robert W.: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 16, Folder 136)
    - Michigan, University of - Lapham, Robert: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 16, Folder 137)
    - Michigan, University of - Population Studies Center: Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 16, Folder 138)
    - Michigan, University of - Takeshita, John: Correspondence: Review of book by Dr. Tenrei: The Prohibition of Induced Abortion and the Eugenic Protection Law (1967 August 7); Report on Korea (1967 March), 1967-1974 (Box 16, Folder 139)
    - Milbank Memorial Fund: Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 16, Folder 140)
    - Minnesota, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 16, Folder 141)
    - Missouri, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 16, Folder 142)
    - Moore, Hugh Fund: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 17, Folder 143)
    - National Academy of Sciences - Correspondence, 1964-1965, 1967-1974 (Box 17, Folder 144-147)
    - National Book Committee, Inc.: Correspondence, 1967 (Box 17, Folder 148)
    - National Science Foundation - Correspondence: Proposal by Population Council "Scientific Work on Population Policy", 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 149)
    - National Science Foundation - Correspondence: Grant Lists and Press Releases, 1967-1969 (Box 17, Folder 150)
    - New England Universities Demographic Research Association (NEUDRA) - Correspondence, proposals, reports, 1973-1975 (Box 18, Folder 151-153)
      Population Council considered a funding grant, but it never reached formal proposal stage.
    - New York, State University of: Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 18, Folder 154)
    - New York, State University of, at Buffalo: Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 18, Folder 155)
    - New York University, 1967-1972 (Box 18, Folder 156)
    - North Carolina, University of - Correspondence, Conference 1973, 1971-1973 (Box 18, Folder 157)
    - North Carolina, University of - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 18, Folder 158)
    - North Carolina, University of - Carolina Population Center: Correspondence, 1967-1974 (Box 19, Folder 159-162)
    - North Carolina, University of - Professor Greenberg: Abortion Study Proposal: Correspondence, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 163)
    - Northwestern University: Correspondence: Preliminary draft "Methods for the Experimenting Society" by Donald C. Campbell, 1968-1974 (Box 20, Folder 164)
    - Notre Dame, University of: Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 165)
    - Ohio State University: Correspondence, 1970, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 166)
    - Oregon, University of: Correspondence, 1968-1973 (Box 20, Folder 167)
    - Organization of American States (OAS) - Proposals for Population Seminar Program, 1972-1973; Correspondence, 1969, 1969, 1972 (Box 20, Folder 168)
    - Organization of American States (OAS) - Final Report, Provisional Verion of Advisory Committee on Population and Development, First Meeting, 1968 July 29-31; Final Report on Population Policies in relation to Development in Latin America, 1967 October 6, 1967-1968 (Box 20, Folder 169)
    - Organization of American States (OAS) - Meeting, 1968 July 29-31 (Box 20, Folder 170)
    - Organization of American States (OAS) - Meeting, Caracas, Venezuela, 1967 September (Box 20, Folder 171)
    - Pan American Health Organization: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 20, Folder 172)
    - Pan American Union: Correspondence, 1967-1969, 1972 (Box 21, Folder 173)
    - Parents' Aid Society: Correspondence, 1968 (Box 21, Folder 174)
    - Pathfinder Fund - Correspondence, 1971-1972, 1974 (Box 21, Folder 175)
    - Pathfinder Fund - Correspondence, Reports, Pamphlets, 1969-1970 (Box 21, Folder 176)
    - Pathfinder Fund - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 21, Folder 177)
    - Peace Corps: Correspondence, Reports, 1966-1971 (Box 21, Folder 178)
    - Pennsylvania State University: Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 21, Folder 179)
    - Pennsylvania, University of - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 21, Folder 180)
    - Pennsylvania, University of - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 21, Folder 181)
    - Pennsylvania, University of - George Povey: Correspondence, 1967-1971 (Box 22, Folder 182)
    - Pittsburgh, University of: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 22, Folder 183)
    - Planned Parenthood Association, Chicago Area: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 22, Folder 184)
    - Planned Parenthood League of Massachusetts: Correspondence, 1970 (Box 22, Folder 185)
    - Planned Parenthood / World Population - Correspondence and News Releases, 1967-1975 (Box 22, Folder 186-188)
    - Population Association of America: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 22, Folder 189)
    - Population Crisis Committee: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 22, Folder 190)
    - Population Institute: Correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box 23, Folder 191)
    - Population Reference Bureau - Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 23, Folder 192)
    - Population Reference Bureau - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 23, Folder 193)
    - Population Reference Bureau - Latin America Department: Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 23, Folder 194)
    - Princeton University: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 23, Folder 195)
    - Princeton University, Office of Population Research: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 23, Folder 196)
    - Public Affairs Committee, Inc.: Correspondence, 1967, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 197)
    - Purdue University: Correspondence, 1969, 1972 (Box 23, Folder 198)
    - Quantitative Analysis Service: Correspondence re: access to computer PDP w/RSTS/I, 1976 (Box 23, Folder 199)
    - Rand Corporation: Correspondence, 1968-1972 (Box 23, Folder 200)
    - Research Triangle Institute: Correspondence, Memos, RTI "Population Concepts", 1968-1972 (Box 24, Folder 202)
    - Resources for the Future: Correspondence, Proposed joint venture between Population Council and Resources for the Future, 1972 (Box 24, Folder 202)
    - Rockefeller Brothers Fund (RBF): Correspondence, Funding Requests and Grants, 1969-1972 (Box 24, Folder 203)
    - Rockefeller Foundation: Correpondence, 1967-1974 (Box 24, Folder 204)
      letters from Population Council to Rockefeller Foundation justifying continuations of funding; letter to Population Council from Rockefeller Foundation accepting justifications; reports on fellowships.
    - Rockefeller Foundation: Lamontagne, Ray: Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 24, Folder 205)
    - Rockefeller Institute (Rockefeller University Computer): Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 24, Folder 206)
    - Rockefeller, John D., 3rd Fund: Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 24, Folder 207)
    - Russell Sage Foundation: Correspondence, 1966-1973 (Box 24, Folder 208)
    - Rutgers University: Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 24, Folder 209)
    - Salisbury Community Foundation: Correspondence, 1967 (Box 24, Folder 210)
    - Sanger, Margaret, Research Bureau: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 24, Folder 211)
    - Scholastic Research Center, National High School Student Survey: Questions Relating to Family Life, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 212)
    - Social Science Research Council: Correspondence, 1967-1973 (Box 25, Folder 213)
    - Southern California, University of: Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 25, Folder 214)
    - Southern Illinois University: Correspondence, 1967 (Box 25, Folder 215)
    - Southern Regional Demographic Group: Newsletters, reports, correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 25, Folder 216)